Hey everyone,
Today, I want to demonstrate how the ZYGO
interferometer that I bought a few months
ago can be used to test optics. In the previous
video, I explained how interferometry works,
what a wavefront is, and discussed the layout
of the instrument. If you are unfamiliar with
interferometry and you haven't seen the previous
video, it might be a good idea to watch that
one first.
This video became quite long, so here is an
overview of the contents, which allows you
to skip ahead if you don’t want to watch
everything. First, I'll show how I replaced
the original low-resolution camera of the
ZYGO with a modern IP camera to record high-resolution
interferograms. And then, we'll take a quick
look at how we can use the camera in combination
with a software called DFT-fringe to create
detailed wavefront maps.
The interferometer came with a reference transmission
sphere, but unfortunately the wavefront documentation
of this item was missing. So, to do meaningful
measurements with it, we first need to establish
its accuracy by performing a calibration.
And with that done, we can test some actual
optics: we'll examine the surface properties
of a high-quality concave wafer scanner mirror
from the 1970s. Then we will take a look at
the wavefront quality of a vintage Canon F/1.2
lens from the early 1980s. We’ll do the
same for a modern full-frame Canon EF zoom
lens. And in the last part of the video, I’ll
show you measurements on the optical properties
of a couple of microscope objectives. All
in all, there is a lot to cover so let’s
dive right in.
As shown in the previous video, the interferometer
is a somewhat basic version, that displayed
low-resolution black and white images on a
monitor for visual evaluation. The instrument
contained two cameras: one for alignment of
the optics under test and one for displaying
the interferogram. Both cameras had a rather
limited resolution of 320x240 pixels. Now,
since this is not 1996 anymore, we can now
do quite a bit better than that.
For the new camera to record the interferograms,
I wanted to use a housed camera with some
kind of mount to be able to attach various
types lenses. And if you look at the layout
of the instrument, there is actually plenty
of space to place such a camera in the instrument
right here. We just need to redirect the light
in the horizontal direction. So what I did
was remove the old camera and the lens, and
then made a bracket that can hold a first
surface mirror under 45-degrees. And this
mirror redirects the vertical beam to a horizontal
one, which can then be captured by the camera.
I tried different kinds of lenses and eventually
settled on this compact 25mm c-mount lens
that works for most situations. It is able
to capture the full field of the interferometer,
while at the same time covering a fairly large
area of the camera chip. But of course, for
specific measurements, it is possible to use
other lenses, like lenses with a longer focal
length or a variable zoom lens. And this can
be very useful if you want to to look at small
details in interferograms. By the way, I left
the original alignment camera where it was,
because it still works fine and you actually
don’t need a lot of resolution to do the
alignment. So the original monitor is still
used in the setup, but only during alignment
procedures.
For powering the IP camera, I connected it
to the 12V power supply already present in
the instrument. And after that, there was
just one more thing left to do and that was
bringing the camera's UTP connection to the
housing of the instrument. For this purpose,
I used a two-sided UTP female connector. One
side connects to the camera, and the other
side connects to the PC. And with that, the
conversion is complete.
Now, I used an IDS ethernet camera for the
conversion, but in fact any camera will do
as long as it can be accessed from a computer,
and the images can be stored to disk. So,
to capture the data what I do is align the
optic to be measured such that a clear interferogram
is visible with well-defined fringes. It helps
if the camera software has a feature to monitor
the maximum fringe intensity so that we can
adjust it to within the linear dynamic range
of the camera. Then I collect a number of
interferograms with somewhat different fringe
angles and spacings. And these can then serve
as a basis for a wavefront analysis.
For the actual wavefront calculations, we'll
used a free software called DFTfringe. It’s
programmed by Dale Eason, who took it upon
himself to make advanced interferometry accessible
to the masses. It is designed with amateur
telescope making in mind, but as will become
clear, its application range is quite a bit
broader than that. I won't delve into all
the functionality of the software. Instead,
I'll just very quickly walk you through the
process of evaluating interferograms and averaging
wavefront data.
So here is the start screen of DFT fringe.
Before it can evaluate the interferograms
correctly, the program requires the input
of a few settings, like what wavelength is
used, and what the fringe spacing in the interferogram
actually represents. In some configurations,
each fringe represents 1 wavelength of phase
shift. But in others, like in autocollimation,
this value actually needs to be set to 0.5.
And when all the parameters are set, we are
basically ready to go.
The software gets us to our results in a few
steps. You start by importing a recorded interferogram
and define the areas you wish to include or
exclude in the wavefront evaluation. If that
is done, the software performs a 2D Fourier
transform on the selected area and allows
us to do a bit of low-frequency spatial filtering.
This filtering can for example remove low
spatial frequencies that are result of the
global intensity variations due to uneven
illumination over the full surface. And after
setting the low-frequency spatial filter,
the image is resampled to a specific size
and from this, the software calculates the
wavefront data.
When the software calculates the wavefront,
it also fits the data to a specific set of
known aberrations. And this feature allows
for removing specific aberrations from your
analysis. For instance, tilt is generally
not an aberration of interest because it describes
the orientation between the reference and
the wavefront under test. And so it has nothing
to do with the shape of either surface. Now,
DFT-fringe allows you to either include or
exclude it from your analysis. You can customize
the presentation of the results and the scale.
For example you can convert wavefront errors
to surface shape errors and choose to present
them in nanometers instead of waves. All in
all, this is a very useful tool for interferometric
fringe analysis and on top of that it can
be downloaded for free.
In all upcoming experiments I will use this
F/0.75 transmission sphere as a reference.
And as I mentioned in the introduction, we
don’t know anything about its accuracy of
shape. So, before we can measure any meaningful
results with it, we need to measure the accuracy
of the reference sphere first. But how do
we do that? We could of course calibrate the
surface of the transmission sphere by comparing
its shape to a more precise reference surface.
But instead, I want to show you another method,
known as the “random ball” method.
The method requires the use of a small smooth
ball with a reflective surface. The surface
of the ball doesn't need to be perfectly spherical,
but I guess it helps if it is quite close-to-spherical.
Now the only thing we need to do for the experiment
is to measure the surface shape of the ball
at many random positions with the reference
sphere and then average these measurements.
The reason that this works is that, if you
collect a lot of samples from a ball surface
even if it’s far from perfect, all the errors
in individual parts of the surface will eventually
average out, and the average will iterate
to the surface equivalent of a perfect sphere.
And when you get to that point, the only error
that remains is the surface error in the reference
sphere because it is systematically present
in all the individual measurements.
You can buy these special high-accuracy SiC
balls for this purpose and these are pretty
expensive. However, there is a much cheaper
way: I just used a precision aluminum oxide
bearing ball that typically costs less than
25 euros online. The largest balls generally
have a diameter of around 10mm and have a
variation in the diameter of about 1 micron.
So they're not incredibly precise, but as
you will see, precise enough for this experiment.
To hold the ball, I made a stand from 3 quarter-inch
bearing balls, glued on top of an aluminum
rod using epoxy. And now we have a calibration
setup ready for less than 30 Euros.
The calibration procedure itself involves
placing this ball at the center of the radius
of curvature of the transmission sphere in
some random orientation. We record an interferogram,
then choose a different (random) area on the
ball, record another one and so on.
Here is what evaluating the results looks
like in practice: what you observe is that
in the individual measurements, the surface
error is generally larger than ¼ of a lambda
and is all over the place. And this is due
to the errors present in the shape of the
ball. But look what happens when we start
averaging these measurements: After 10 measurements,
the error has basically dropped down to 1/10th
of a lambda P-V. And by adding more and more
measurement to the average, we can gradually
bring this down even further. Until after
evaluating about 50 interferograms, we do
not see improvement any more in the result.
And at that point we know that the error that
remains is basically the error in the transmission
sphere reference.
If we look at the accuracy of shape in the
spherical reference, it is about 1/20 of a
wavelength peak to valley. And we will consider
this to be the wavefront accuracy over the
full area of the transmission sphere. Now
in all the upcoming tests, we will only use
a small fraction of this reference surface,
which will make the accuracy of the tests
quite a bit higher than the 1/20th of a lambda.
DFTfringe presents the value of the Strehl
ratio quite prominently. And I actually discussed
Strehl ratio in another video. Now I must
admit, Strehl ratio is not the most common
parameter used in the specification of the
optical quality of lenses. But for specifying
wavefront performance close to the diffraction
limit, I think it is a very useful parameter.
What it describes is basically just the ratio
between where wave energy actually ends up
in an image, compared to where it should have
ended up if the optic were perfect. So here
is a graph of an intensity profile of an imperfect
optic and of a perfect optic. To calculate
the Strehl we take the area that is under
both curves and name this B, and then divide
this by the area under the perfect curve,
so area A. This represents the fraction of
the light energy that goes to where it should
have gone in an image.
Since Strehl ratio is a fraction, its value
is between 0 and 1. And a value of 1 only
applies to an optic that performs at the theoretical
limit. Now, roughly speaking, an optic with
a Strehl ratio value above 0.83 is considered
to be “diffraction limited” What this
doesn’t mean is that the optic is performing
perfectly in this region. It just means that
the dominant factor for reduced sharpness
is because of diffraction, for example because
of a limited aperture. And to a lesser degree
it is due to the imperfections in things like
surface shape. So, in a sense the value of
0.83 is similar to stating that ¼ lambda
Peak to valley wavefront error is “diffraction
limited”. Because both these values are
kind of arbitrary definitions of what is meant
by “diffraction limited”.
So our reference surface turns out to be very
accurate, as we can conclude from both the
Strehl value as well as from the PV wavefront
error. But of course, that is kind of essential
if you want to use it to measure optical quality
of other objects in the high-end of the range.
The first thing we are going to measure is
the surface shape of this spherical Zerodur
mirror. It’s about 250mm in diameter and
has a radius of curvature of 350mm. I bought
the mirror about 10 years ago on eBay for
around 100 Euros. The reflective coating was
in pretty bad shape, so I removed it. But
the remaining surface reflectivity is 4%,
which is ideal in this test setup. The mirror
itself is from a 1970s Perkin-Elmer wafer
scanner system. This was the first commercial
photolithographic system that used non-contact
exposure of silicon wafers. So given its original
application, you’d expect this mirror to
be quite accurate.
The way we measure this mirror is with the
focus of the reference element in the center
of the radius of curvature of the mirror.
So, the tightly focused light beam from the
interferometer expands and reflects off the
mirror surface. It then returns along approximately
the same path and is recombined with the spherical
reference wavefront that reflects of the reference
element. And any deviations from spherical
in the mirror surface will cause phase shifts
between the light reflecting off the mirror
surface and the spherical reference. And this
can then be observed as interference.
Here are a few typical interferograms that
were measured with this mirror under a slight
tilt. Even though the mirror is strongly curved,
you can observe that in the measurements,
it only covers about half the diameter of
the total measurement area available. And
this makes our accuracy of measurement much
higher than 1/20th of a wavelength.
So from the interferograms just collected,
the wavefront differences between the mirror
surface and that of the reference element
is calculated in DFTfringe. you can see that
the peak to valley accuracy of this mirror
itself is around 1/10th of a wavelength. In
terms of surface shape accuracy, this means
that the mirror never deviates more than around
30nm of that of a perfect sphere. Anyway,
being able to measure with this level of precision
is actually pretty cool and it gave me confidence
that the instrument performs as expected.
By the way, if you have ever tried to make
a telescope mirror by hand yourself, you might
observe something familiar in the wavefron
plot: the mirror has a slightly turned down
edge, although very small, around 15nm or
so.
Next on the list of items to test is this
Canon FD 55mm F/1.2 lens. This is a rather
famous vintage lens in the sense that it was
actually the first consumer lens containing
an aspherical element. With its F/1.2 aperture,
it’s very light sensitive and therefore
well suited for indoor photography without
using a flash. The earliest versions of this
lens introduced in 1971, contained radioactive
Thorium Oxide, but this one, which was bought
by my father in march 1980, does not contain
Thorium. Therefore, it also does not display
the characteristic radiation browning observed
in radioactive lenses. On top of that it has
lived in a box most of its life so it’s
in nearly pristine condition.
For testing the wavefront deformation in this
lens, we utilize a configuration called autocollimation,
which is schematically depicted here. Because
the light passes through the lens twice in
this test, many aberrations are measured to
be twice as large as they would be with a
single pass. So when this configuration is
used, it requires us to interpret the fringe
spacing as equivalent with only 0.5 wavelength
instead of 1 wavelength.
Before I show you the result of the measurement,
I should mention that doing a wavefront measurement
on a lens is not in any way representative
for overall lens performance. Basically, we
are testing with only one particular wavelength
of light on the optical axis with the focus
setting to infinity. So, factors like chromatic
aberrations, off-axis performance in the image
field and the at proximity are not included
in this test. I've actually made a video on
how to quantitatively measure all these aspects
using another method and obtain a more holistic
performance. But even with all the limitations,
I think it is worthwhile to take a look at
the wavefront error that this lens introduces.
So here is the wavefront error of the lens
at its full aperture and as you can see, it’s
is actually pretty large. The total P-V wavefront
error is more than 3 lambda and the most apparent
errors are spherical aberration and some astigmatisms.
The Strehl ratio is quite disappointing as
well. As a consequence, this lens can never
provide high sharpness images at the maximum
aperture. Now, it’s interesting to see what
happens if we limit the aperture of this lens
to let’s say to F/4.0. By doing that, we
will lose a lot of light, about 90%. But this
also limits the wavefront error to the one
present in this central part here. So, if
we do the same wavefront analysis at F/4,
suddenly the lens performs diffraction limited.
Because reducing aperture to F/4 eliminates
almost all of the spherical error and the
astigmatism which is present in the wavefront
at full aperture.
Here is a comparison of the text on a permanent
marker shot with F/1.2 and F/4 on an aps-c
sensor. It’s clear that the 3-lambda wavefront
error is influencing the sharpness and contrast
pretty badly. So, I guess the only way to
use this lens effectively is to always set
it to a smaller aperture whenever there is
sufficient light available, otherwise you’ll
end up with very soft images.
The Canon EF 24 to 105mm full frame zoom lens
is next on our list. I just want to take a
very brief look at it, mainly because I sometimes
use it for my YouTube videos. With its maximum
aperture of F/4 over the whole zoom range
it is not particularly photon hungry. But
it always produces excellent image sharpness,
which made me curious about how small the
wavefront errors in a high-quality lens are.
It was measured in the same way as the F/1.2
lens, so in autocollimation. And here are
the wavefront errors at focal length settings
of 24mm, 50mm and 105mm. The largest wavefront
errors are found at 105mm focal distance,
where the Strehl ratio has dropped to 0.6.
Which by the way is still a very decent value.
In the center of the range, its performance
is basically diffraction limited. So concluding:
this lens performs well in the full zoom range.
That is of course, within all the limitations
of the current testing method.
If you made it this far into the video you
are probably more than averagely interested
in optics. So, for this last part I thought
I’d present measurements that I did on microscope
objectives. All objectives presented here
are all so called “infinity corrected”
objectives. This means that they are designed
to work in combination with a so-called tube
lens rather than create an image directly
like is the case with a proximity-corrected
objectives. Since infinity corrected objectives
basically project their image at infinity,
this allows us to correctly use the autocollimation
configuration for testing.
Unlike camera lenses, microscope objectives
aren't specified by focal length and maximum
focal distance to aperture ratio. Instead,
they are characterized by magnification and
numerical aperture. I’ll very briefly discuss
these two aspects first.
Magnification describes the ratio between
the object size and image size that a particular
microscope objective is designed for. You
can of course try to use it at a different
magnification by changing both the lens-object
distance and the lens-image distance. But
if you do that, it will not perform optimally.
And this is important because microscope optics
is required to work close to the theoretical
best performance. So in this sense, a microscope
objective is a bit different from a camera
lens, which is basically designed to give
you acceptable image quality over a wide range
of object to lens distances.
Now, specifying a high magnification is only
useful if the sharpness in the image keeps
up with the magnification that is specified.
And that is why the Magnification and Numerical
Aperture of objectives are related, because
Numerical Aperture is a key parameter for
resolving small features.
By definition, the NA is equal to the refractive
index of the medium that contains the object,
times the SIN() of the maximum angle theta
at which light originating from the object
can be captured. This means that NA increases
with the refractive index of the medium and
with the value of theta. Now, since all the
objectives I will discuss today are intended
for use in air and not in water- or oil, we
can simplify things because the refractive
index of air is 1. So for now we can just
ignore the refractive index which means that
NA in all cases discussed here is just equal
to the sin() of theta.
The exact reason why NA is the key parameter
for achieving a high sharpness is quite fascinating.
But it is kind of a rabbit hole, which I don’t
want to dive into now. Today I will just show
you the formula. So, the size of the smallest
features that can theoretically be resolved
by a microscope objective are proportional
to a constant, times the wavelength of light,
divided by the numerical aperture. This means
that it is possible to resolve smaller features
by either using a shorter wavelength of light,
or use a higher NA.
This relationship explains why magnification
and numerical aperture are so closely related
in the specification of microscope objectives.
Because attempting to pair a high magnification
with a low numerical aperture is pretty useless:
it will just result in a magnified image of
poor sharpness.
Let’s have a look at the measurements on
this Nikon 10x objective with a N.A. of 0.3.
Here is an image of the wavefront error of
this objective and it shows us that the errors
are in fact very small. The wavefront is accurate
within seven hundredths of a wavelength for
the entire aperture, the Strehl is 0.99, so
this is looking great. The major contribution
in the surface error is actually a very slight
spherical aberration, but all in all, this
is really a top-quality piece.
Now, let's examine a different objective,
like this 20x Leica Fluotar with a NA of 0.5,
and do the same wavefront measurement. Interestingly,
the spherical aberration in this objective
is noticably more pronounced. Both the total
peak-valley error as well as the Strehl ratio
is only just on the good side of the diffraction
limit. Now, it might be tempting to conclude
that this objective is not as good as the
previous one, but that's not the case. The
reason behind the spherical aberration is
in this particular number that can be found
on the objective. The number represents the
optimum cover slip thickness in millimeters
for this objective.
So, what the manufacturer assumes is that
you are going to use a glass cover slip when
you use your microscope and it therefore it
has already compensated the optical properties
for a specific glass thickness. Now, you might:
think huh 0.17mm of glass thickness, how is
that ever going to influence the focus? And
indeed, with low numerical aperture optics
there will generally not be a problem. However,
with increasing NA, even a glass plate this
thin can introduce a significant spherical
aberration. This is illustrated in this ray
tracing figure for a 0.7 NA. In a perfect
optic, all rays will end in a single point.
But add a cover glass and suddenly the area
where the rays end up has significant size.
Now of course the previous wavefront measurement
was done without a cover slip. So, the question
is what happens if we add a cover slip in
the light path? I quickly tried this with
a glass thickness of 0.16mm, so close to the
optimum value and it resulted in this measurement:
it reduced the spherical aberration quite
a bit. And so, this is something to realize
when you use a high-NA objectives: that it
can only perform at its peak performance when
used in combination with the cover slip thickness
specified.
So a few years ago, I bought this unmarked
NIKON 20x Plan APO OEM objective for use in
my maskless wafer stepper. These Nikon objectives
can be purchased on eBay for around 100 dollars
apiece and are widely available. It was in
perfect shape when it got here but when I
started using it, something was a bit off,
dependent on how I used it exactly. Now, when
I published the video on the maskless wafer
stepper, people at a forum called photomicrography.net
made me aware of the fact that these particular
types of objectives aren't optically the same
as the corresponding standard Nikon microscope
objectives; they are actually modified versions
that are designed for a different cover slip
thickness. The forum thread on this subject
mentioned that these perform better when used
in combination with 2 or 3 cover slips. And
since I now have an interferometer available
let’s see if we can narrow this value down
a bit further.
Here is the spherical aberration of the objective
without a cover slip. The wavefront error
is 1 lambda, so without a correction, it will
certainly perform very poorly. Here I summarized
the individual wavefront measurements for
0, 1, 2, 3 and 4 cover slips. I think the
effect of adding more glass is pretty clear.
You can see that the wavefront error sort
of flips over between 2 and 3 cover slips
of glass thickness.
What we can do now is take for example the
peak to valley spherical aberration from these
measurements and plot the values as a function
of the total glass thickness in a graph. And
by fitting a line through these data, we find
that a minimum aberration is at around 0.42-0.43mm.
And this thickness is right between 2 and
3 cover slips, like it was stated on the forum.
Here is a similar graph that I made for the
maximum Strehl ratio, which yields exactly
the same outcome. So, if we were to add a
0.42 mm glass sheet when using it, we can
effectively get rid of the huge spherical
aberration completely and use this objective
at its maximum performance level again.
Okay, we’ve finally come to the end of the
video. I hope I gave you some ideas of how
interferometry can be used for optical testing.
Thanks for watching.