Hi everyone,
Today I want to talk about optical interferometry,
a method that is frequently used to measure the
properties of optical components and systems.
What initially made me want to do a video about
this subject is this ZYGO interferometer, that I
bought a while ago second hand. A new instrument
of this type is financially far out of my reach,
and I must admit, this one wasn’t a bargain
either. But the thing is, I’ve wanted to own
a high-quality interferometer for a long time,
if only to get away from the DIY-setups I’ve
used so far. And since these instruments are
not abundantly available second hand, I just
had to take this rare opportunity to buy one.
In case you have no idea what this instrument is:
with it you can very accurately measure the
shape of flat and spherical optical interfaces,
like the ones you find on lenses and mirrors. And
with accurately I mean: in the nanometer range.
But not only that, you can also measure the
performance of complete optical systems. So,
a good interferometer is an indispensable tool for
anyone involved in optical fabrication. Because
in the end, the quality of your optics is mainly
limited by the quality of your testing methods.
This particular instrument was produced
by ZYGO in August of 1996. It was sold
to Philips Electronics in Eindhoven,
where it was used to check the surface
shape of lenses for special optical
disk drives. From what I understood,
some of these lenses were produced from small
polished glass balls. These were cut in pieces,
and then transformed into very short
focal distance lenses. Now, at some point,
the activity was transferred to a Philips spin-off
called Anteryon and the interferometer was sold to
an employee, who basically stored it for a couple
of years. He then sold it to me, together with a
black and white monitor and the transmission
sphere that was used to test the lenses.
In this video, I’ll first discuss
the principle behind interferometry,
and then we will look at the layout of the
instrument and how it works exactly. And in
an upcoming video I will show how I pimped the
instrument a bit with a modern ccd camera.
As I said earlier, in optics manufacture,
interferometry is a frequently used method
to characterize both optical surfaces as well
as complete systems. The method is based on
analyzing interference patterns and extract so
called “wavefront” information from them and I
will discuss the meaning of the word wavefront in
a second. Interferometry is an extremely sensitive
and accurate method that can be used to establish
the general shape of an interface, but also things
like waviness or even surface roughness. It
does also have some limitations: The measurement
range is generally fairly limited to several
microns. Also, it’s unsuitable for interfaces that
contain sharp step-like height features, because
these cannot be unambiguously identified. So,
in general, interferometry is most accurate when
the surfaces we want to test are fairly smooth.
Now, I just mentioned the word “wavefront”,
which I think is not a trivial concept.
I guess we have all experienced wavefronts at some
point in our lives but I’m not referring to those.
In optics a wavefront is actually a continuous set
of points that have identical phase. So, what does
that mean? Well, from a classical viewpoint, light
is an electromagnetic field that harmonically
oscillates and propagates in space. And at any
given point in this process, the electric and
magnetic field components can be described by
the Maxwell equations. So here I’ve tried to
schematically draw the electromagnetic field in
a somewhat larger volume and if you examine the
phase of these waves, you can identify planes
where the phase of the electromagnetic field
is identical. And a continuous set of points that
have the same phase value is called a wavefront.
One property of a wavefront is that its shape
is always transverse or perpendicular to the
local direction of wave propagation. Here
this is illustrated for a few differently
shaped wavefronts where the arrows indicate the
direction of wave propagation. Now in general,
phase relationships for different points in
space are only well-defined when the waves
have one specific wavelength. And if we want to
do interferometry, it is vital that the light we
use is of one particular wavelength, which
is also called monochromatic light. And in
the rest of the video, I’ll assume that the
light used is more or less monochromatic.
A frequently used way to generate monochromatic
radiation is by means of a laser. This is because,
the process of stimulated emission which takes
place in the laser cavity, favors the generation
of light in a very narrow wavelength range.
Also, the wavefront exiting the laser cavity is
virtually flat over the aperture. And because the
light has an extremely well-defined wavelength,
in other words it has a very narrow spectral
bandwidth, phase relationships in the field
exiting the laser can be preserved over long
distances. Another way to say this is that lasers
have a large coherence length, which is generally
between half a meter up to several kilometers for
certain special types of lasers. In practice
this means that, if we take 2 points A and B in
the light path and we look at the variations in
the phase difference between these 2 points, we
will find that these will be relatively small. And
the distance over which variations in phase remain
acceptable is called the coherence length. As you
can see from this equation, the coherence length
(Lc) is inversely proportional to the spectral
band width (delta nu) of the light source. And
so light sources with a very narrow emission line
will generally have a long coherence length.
Another source of monochromatic light frequently
used in interferometry is the low-pressure sodium
lamp, which mainly generates light in a
narrow emission band at 589nm. However,
the spectral bandwidth of the Sodium emission
line is much broader than that of lasers and
the phase relationships generally only
hold over distances smaller than a mm.
Now, measuring the shape of a wavefront
directly in the visible part of the
electromagnetic spectrum is not easy and that is
because of the very high frequencies involved.
For electromagnetic radiation of longer
wavelengths, like for example radio waves,
we can measure the phase of the alternating fields
directly. And that is because the oscillations
have a relatively low frequency, say generally
somewhere in the mega- or giga- Hertz range.
And so, we can point a bunch of antennas to the
sky, measure the Electromagnetic signals that
are received in each of them and establish the
shape of the wavefront for a particular frequency
by looking for phase correlations. And based on
this information we can then identify the exact
direction from which the radiation is emitted. But
visible light has a frequency more than a thousand
times higher than even the highest frequency
radio waves. And for frequencies this high, it is
technically infeasible to measure phase directly
for an oscillating electromagnetic field.
However, what we can easily measure with
optical detectors, like CCD- or CMOS-sensors,
is spatial intensity variations. And
that is where interferometry comes in:
instead of trying to measure the phase in light
directly, this method works by studying the
interference patterns resulting from the addition
of a second wavefront that has a known shape.
Let me start by showing you a very simple
example of how this works in light.
For this experiment we need a monochromatic
light source and a flat surface. As a light
source we’ll use a sodium lamp and for the
surface we will use a flat optical test glass.
Now, a typical air-glass interface
reflects about 4% of the incident light
and with a uniform light source,
we observe a uniform reflection.
Let’s now place 2 differently shaped surfaces on
top of this reference surface for evaluation. What
we observe is that these objects show 2 different
interference patterns. The part to the left,
shows straight lines with equal spacing. And the
one to the right, displays these curved lines or
circular fringes, depending on the exact surface
orientation. Now, it’s these intensity variations
that actually contain detailed information about
the difference in shape between reference surface
and the two surfaces under test. We just need
to know how to interpret what we see exactly.
So, what do we see? Well let me explain with
an animation. I admit, the following is a
simplification and it’s not correctly visualizing
the physics, but it’s actually quite illustrative.
Here is a wavefront that has just reflected off
a flat reference surface, so this wavefront is
basically also flat. And so the image shows a
2D cross section of the flat optical wavefronts.
If we place a sensor in the path of the
light, we can measure the intensity,
and what we observe is that it is basically the
same everywhere and this tells us exactly nothing
about the shape of the wavefront. Now, let’s add
a second wavefront that has reflected of a second
surface that is slightly tilted. In this example
the wavefront is also flat and what we observe
is that the intensity now becomes non-uniformly.
And this is caused by constructive and destructive
interference between the 2 reflected wavefronts
at the second interface. Here, the electromagnetic
field is the linear sum of the contributions
of the fields of the 2 wavefronts. And so,
in some points where these contributions are
always in phase, they add up. On the other hand,
in places where the two are exactly in out
of phase, the field contributions cancel each
other out and if they are of equal amplitude,
effectively the resulting field becomes zero.
In the case of 2 flat wavefronts, we will observe
linear and equally spaced fringes. The density of
the interference pattern itself is dependent
on the wedge or angle between the surfaces.
And the position of the fringes is dependent
on the distance between the two surfaces. Now,
you might think that linear and equally spaced
fringes are indicative for the presence of 2 flat
surfaces. And that is partly correct, but 2 curved
wavefronts with the same radius of curvature will
actually also display linear and equally spaced
fringes, when displaced or tilted. However,
when two wavefronts have different radii, this
results in curved fringes. This is for example
the case when we have a flat- and a spherical
wavefront interfering. Or when we have 2 spherical
wavefronts that have a different radius curvature.
So, I guess it is important to realize that
the observed interference pattern only gives us
information about differences in wavefront shape.
In the example just shown with the sodium lamp
light, we only observe interference between
interfaces when they are placed very close
together. And that is because of the limited
coherence length of the light. So whether we see a
clear interference pattern is dependent on whether
stable phase relationships exist between the
reflections coming off the two surfaces at the
point where they start interfering. This means
that with a coherence length smaller than a mm,
the surfaces need to be quite close to each
other in order to observe interference fringes.
Now I just stated that in constructive
interference, the electromagnetic fields
add up and in destructive interference, the
2 contributions cancel each other out. So,
what does this mean for intensity? Well,
light intensity is equivalent to the power
per unit of surface and so it is actually
not the same thing as the magnitude of
the electromagnetic field. In fact, intensity
scales with the square of this field. And so,
if we have 2 reflections of equal magnitude, say
both are 4%, this means that for the location of
constructive interference, intensity could be
4 times as high. And that is actually what is
generally observed in interference patterns:
that the intensity in the bright areas is
much brighter than the sum of the 2 individual
intensities. But of course, if we look on average,
the intensity over the whole area will still
equal to the sum of the 2 individual intensities.
Anyway, enough background. Let’s return to the
ZYGO interferometer itself and take a peek under
the hood to see what’s going on inside. In order
to do that we need to remove 2 different lids:
the outer one is made of plastic and is
basically just cosmetic. The second one is
made out of aluminum sheet metal and is intended
as RF-shielding for the electronics inside.
First thing you notice is, that it isn’t awfully
full inside. There is a helium Neon laser with
its high-voltage power supply. Then there are a
few optical components like a steering mirror for
the laser beam, a variable filter that can be
moved mechanically using a long rod. This rod
also operates a switch, that activates either of
2 pcb-cameras that are also found in the top part
of the interferometer. The cameras by the way
have CCD-chips of about 6x4mm in size and are
fairly low resolution. Both cameras have lenses
mounted in front of them. One of the camera is
above a tiny beam splitter, and the other one is
above a diffusor with a crosshair printed on it.
In the bottom compartment, behind the lid
here, we find a mains 12V DC power supply,
a large beam splitter, a mirror under 45
degrees and 4-inch collimation lens. And
apart from a few brackets and mounts that hold
the optics together, that is basically it.
So you might wonder: why was this thing the
price of a luxury car back in 1996? Well,
apart from I suspect a healthy profit margin,
there are several reasons: of course, it’s not
really a mass manufactured item. But another
reason is that every component inside appears
to be of very high quality. Take for example
the Helium Neon laser: according to the label,
the tube has been specifically selected for this
type of instrument. Why? Well, if we look at the
specification of the coherence length of the
interferometer, we see that it is larger than
100m. This means that the wavelength variations
in the laser light need to be extremely low,
so that phase relationships hold over distances of
more than 100m. Now, I calculated what this means
in terms of frequency stability and found that
variations in the frequency of the 632nm light
cannot be more than 2. 10-7 percent. And so, this
means that not just any random laser will do.
So let me take you through the functionality of
all the components step by step using schematics.
Here is the Helium-Neon laser, which
outputs a highly coherent beam of
light. The direction of the beam can be
optimized with a small steering mirror,
after which the beam goes through the variable
attenuation filter. This filter allows adjustment
of the general brightness of the laser beam.
After having passed the attenuation filter, the
beam is going into a gradient index lens, which
is connected to a very small beam splitter.
Now, a gradient index lens is a small glass rod
that contains a gradient in refractive index,
that runs from the center to edge of the rod.
Since the refractive index has the highest value
in the center, the optical wave front in the
laser beam is gradually delayed more towards
the center of the rod. The wavefront therefore
becomes curved, which effectively results in
focusing of the light into a tight focal point.
And after passing this focal point, the beam
expands again into a nicely spherical wavefront. A
small beam splitter sends the spherical wavefront
to the partially reflective surface of a
second, much larger beam splitter. This
surface reflects the light towards a collimation
lens, where the light exits the instrument.
The function of the collimation lens is to
convert the spherical wavefront into a flat
wavefront of 4 inches in diameter. And this
flat wavefront can serve as the basis for all
kinds of interferometric tests. For example, we
can place 2 partially reflective flat interfaces
into this output beam, one being a reference
interface and one being the interface that
we like to test for flatness. And due to
the large coherence length of the light,
more than 100m, these interfaces don’t have
the be necessarily very close together.
The light reflecting off these surfaces
is directed back into the interferometer
approximately along the same path as it came
from, goes through the small beam splitter
again and is then collimated and projected on
a CCD chip. And this allows us to observe the
interference pattern between the 2 reflections
and evaluate this visually on the monitor.
Now, to steer the light of both the reference
and test surface exactly back through the tiny
beam splitter here, is pretty hard. And
you don’t see anything with camera 1,
until things are almost perfectly aligned. So, to
make life a lot easier, the people at ZYGO added
this alignment functionality to the system. Part
of the light from the reflections can pass this
larger beam splitter. This part continues straight
on, is reflected at a 90 degrees angle and then
reaches a glass diffuser plate that contains a
cross-hair pattern. Because this diffusor plate is
exactly at the focal distance of the collimation
lens, the reflections create tiny spots here. And
their positions can be observed by camera 2 that
is only intended for alignment purposes. Now,
this alignment unit has a much larger field of
view and what we can do now is simply align the
position of surface reflections such that they
are at the center of the cross-hair. And when
that is the case, the system is automatically also
aligned on camera 1 and we can immediately observe
an interferogram. Now, the interferometers
that I made myself did not have this kind of
feature and it must admit that this makes
aligning optics really a piece of cake.
Here you see the location of the collimation
lens, viewed from the outside of the instrument.
In front of it is an adjustment mechanism
that is intended for mounting various
reference surfaces to the interferometer
directly, like the F/0.75 transmission
sphere that came with the interferometer. The
adjustment mechanism has 2 degrees of freedom,
which are tip and tilt. This allows the angle of
the transmission reference to be oriented with
respect to the surface under test.
When testing optical components,
you generally test the surface shape before
the interfaces get coated. And so in the case
of glass this means that they reflect around 4% of
the incident light. So, the transmission reference
also needs to reflect around 4% back into the
interferometer to get high-contrast fringes.
To test spherical surfaces, you need a spherical
reference surface that somehow reflects 4% of the
light exiting the interferometer right back into
the instrument. Now the way this is achieved is as
follows: here I’ve drawn a schematic of the inside
of a transmission sphere assembly to show you how
that is achieved. The reference surface is the
last interface of the assembly, here indicated in
yellow. All the other surfaces are anti-reflection
coated for the laser wavelength, but even more
importantly, they are also designed in such a way,
that the light reaches the reference interface
exactly perpendicular. And this means that it is
the only interface in the transmission sphere that
sends a reflection back where it came from and
then enters the interferometer as a collimated
beam. Of course, 96% of the light continues on
to the surface under test, which also reflects
around 4%. And so we observe the interference
occurring between these 2 interfaces.
With a spherical transmission reference, we
can test convex- as well as concave optics.
For convex optics, only radii smaller than the
radius of the transmission sphere itself can be
tested. For concave optics, the only limitation
for the radius to be tested is that it should be
less than half of the maximum coherence length
of the light source which is in this case 50m.
Now I want to save most of the experiments
that I had in mind for another video,
but let’s just do one simple experiment. For
this test, we’ll just use the flat wavefront
exiting the instrument. And what we will try to
measure is the difference in shape between the
2 surfaces of a Zerodur test glass. This test
glass has one side which I know is very flat,
around 1/20th of a wavelength. And this is
going to be our reference interface. But the
other side is somewhat less flat. And what
we’ll try to find out is how much that is.
The two interfaces are spaced 20 mm apart and
both reflect about 4% of the incident light. So
we can just place the disk in the beam exiting
the interferometer, align the position of the
2 reflections simultaneously and then look at
the interference pattern. And this is what it
looks like. As you can see, we get a nice and
clear interference pattern, which by the way is
extremely stable with no effects of vibrations
from the environment. That is because the two
surfaces are basically mechanically connected
to each other by a solid piece of Zerodur.
Now, the small circular spots are just dust
particles in the optical path and these are
not important for our evaluation. All the
information about the difference in shape
and orientation between the 2 surfaces is
contained in the 4 more or less vertical
fringes. And because we know that
one side is almost perfectly flat,
any curvature in the fringe pattern is the
result of non-flatness of the second surface.
So, let’s try to evaluate this pattern visually.
The most obvious feature is of course the presence
of the 4 vertical fringes, that indicate that
there is a wedge between the 2 interfaces in
horizontal direction. And we can calculate how
large this wedge is, based on the number of
fringes. It is a little over 4 Lambda wavefront,
meaning that there is a wedge half of that between
the 2 surfaces, so just 2 wavelengths. Why
half? Well, that is because in reflection,
any deviations in surface shape, lead to twice
the deviation in the wavefront shape. And so,
deviations in surface shape are only
half of that observed in the wavefront.
Now, since the wavelength of the laser is 632.8nm
and the wedge is 2 lambda between the 2 surface
this, would mean a gradient in distance of
approx. 1.3 microns. But there is a little
catch in this case. Because we are comparing 2
surfaces with Zerodur between them, we should
actually use the wavelength in this material.
Which means that we should divide the wavelength
in air or vacuum by the refractive index of
Zerodur, which is 1.54. So this means that the
wedge is actually only 840nm. But which side is
thicker? It’s hard to tell because as for wedge,
we would see the same type of interference pattern
in either case. So at this point, we don’t know.
Okay, let’s for a moment focus on the curvature
of the fringes now, which indicates a difference
in the radius between the 2 surfaces. If
we look at how much the curvature in the
fringes deviates from a straight line, we see
that it is largest here in the center, and it
is about 0.4 times the fringe spacing, which
translates to 0.4 wavelength of height difference
between edge and center of the disk. For the
surface error, which again is half of that,
we find 0.2 wavelengths, Now, since we also
need to use the wavelength inside Zerodur here,
this means that the surface curvature is 0.2*times
the wavelength divided by the refractive index,
which results in a value of 82nm. But
in which direction is the curve? Is the
surface under test 82nm concave or convex? As
with the direction of the wedge, there is no
easy way to tell. So now we end up with these 4
configurations of which only one can be correct.
With a little logic though, you could at this
point already discard 2 of these as infeasible.
But of course, you want to know exactly which
configuration of the 4 is correct, right?
So, if that is indeed the case, figure it out
yourself. You just need a 2 more pieces of
information. Here is the first hint: if I press
my finger against the backside of the disk,
so on the surface under test, we can observe
that the interferogram changes due to temperature
increase of the material by the heat of my finger.
Locally, it is only a few degrees Celsius higher,
but the effect is very noticeable because
we are measuring in the nanometer range.
Now, the second piece of information you need
is about the expansion coefficient of the
material. As you can see from the specifications
of Zerodur, it can be either positive or negative.
But this piece of Zerodur has a positive
coefficient of thermal expansion, which
means it expands with temperature increase. And
with these 2 additional pieces of information,
it is possible tell which of these 4 options
is correct. Now, the first person to make
a comment with the correct answer and
course why, owns the pinned comment.
Okay, so the latter was a very brief explanation
of how you can evaluate interferograms visually.
And, the above example was actually relatively
easy. Imagine your interferogram looks something
like this. Or this. In these cases, it would be
quite a bit more challenging to make accurate
statements about the exact surface shape. This
is why in the next video about this subject,
I have replaced the current analog camera with a
high-resolution IP-camera. This allows for very
detailed evaluation of interferograms using
software. And with the help of this software,
we can measure wedges, angles, surface
curvature, and even the effects of warm
fingers very accurately. Also, we will take a look
at how to measure the shape of various optical
surfaces, and the quality of lens assemblies. So,
hopefully I’ll see you in the next video again.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------
# [English] Optical Interferometry Part 2_ Measuring Optics with a Zygo GPI LC
Hey everyone,
Today, I want to demonstrate how the ZYGO
interferometer that I bought a few months
ago can be used to test optics. In the previous
video, I explained how interferometry works,
what a wavefront is, and discussed the layout
of the instrument. If you are unfamiliar with
interferometry and you haven't seen the previous
video, it might be a good idea to watch that
one first.
This video became quite long, so here is an
overview of the contents, which allows you
to skip ahead if you don’t want to watch
everything. First, I'll show how I replaced
the original low-resolution camera of the
ZYGO with a modern IP camera to record high-resolution
interferograms. And then, we'll take a quick
look at how we can use the camera in combination
with a software called DFT-fringe to create
detailed wavefront maps.
The interferometer came with a reference transmission
sphere, but unfortunately the wavefront documentation
of this item was missing. So, to do meaningful
measurements with it, we first need to establish
its accuracy by performing a calibration.
And with that done, we can test some actual
optics: we'll examine the surface properties
of a high-quality concave wafer scanner mirror
from the 1970s. Then we will take a look at
the wavefront quality of a vintage Canon F/1.2
lens from the early 1980s. We’ll do the
same for a modern full-frame Canon EF zoom
lens. And in the last part of the video, I’ll
show you measurements on the optical properties
of a couple of microscope objectives. All
in all, there is a lot to cover so let’s
dive right in.
As shown in the previous video, the interferometer
is a somewhat basic version, that displayed
low-resolution black and white images on a
monitor for visual evaluation. The instrument
contained two cameras: one for alignment of
the optics under test and one for displaying
the interferogram. Both cameras had a rather
limited resolution of 320x240 pixels. Now,
since this is not 1996 anymore, we can now
do quite a bit better than that.
For the new camera to record the interferograms,
I wanted to use a housed camera with some
kind of mount to be able to attach various
types lenses. And if you look at the layout
of the instrument, there is actually plenty
of space to place such a camera in the instrument
right here. We just need to redirect the light
in the horizontal direction. So what I did
was remove the old camera and the lens, and
then made a bracket that can hold a first
surface mirror under 45-degrees. And this
mirror redirects the vertical beam to a horizontal
one, which can then be captured by the camera.
I tried different kinds of lenses and eventually
settled on this compact 25mm c-mount lens
that works for most situations. It is able
to capture the full field of the interferometer,
while at the same time covering a fairly large
area of the camera chip. But of course, for
specific measurements, it is possible to use
other lenses, like lenses with a longer focal
length or a variable zoom lens. And this can
be very useful if you want to to look at small
details in interferograms. By the way, I left
the original alignment camera where it was,
because it still works fine and you actually
don’t need a lot of resolution to do the
alignment. So the original monitor is still
used in the setup, but only during alignment
procedures.
For powering the IP camera, I connected it
to the 12V power supply already present in
the instrument. And after that, there was
just one more thing left to do and that was
bringing the camera's UTP connection to the
housing of the instrument. For this purpose,
I used a two-sided UTP female connector. One
side connects to the camera, and the other
side connects to the PC. And with that, the
conversion is complete.
Now, I used an IDS ethernet camera for the
conversion, but in fact any camera will do
as long as it can be accessed from a computer,
and the images can be stored to disk. So,
to capture the data what I do is align the
optic to be measured such that a clear interferogram
is visible with well-defined fringes. It helps
if the camera software has a feature to monitor
the maximum fringe intensity so that we can
adjust it to within the linear dynamic range
of the camera. Then I collect a number of
interferograms with somewhat different fringe
angles and spacings. And these can then serve
as a basis for a wavefront analysis.
For the actual wavefront calculations, we'll
used a free software called DFTfringe. It’s
programmed by Dale Eason, who took it upon
himself to make advanced interferometry accessible
to the masses. It is designed with amateur
telescope making in mind, but as will become
clear, its application range is quite a bit
broader than that. I won't delve into all
the functionality of the software. Instead,
I'll just very quickly walk you through the
process of evaluating interferograms and averaging
wavefront data.
So here is the start screen of DFT fringe.
Before it can evaluate the interferograms
correctly, the program requires the input
of a few settings, like what wavelength is
used, and what the fringe spacing in the interferogram
actually represents. In some configurations,
each fringe represents 1 wavelength of phase
shift. But in others, like in autocollimation,
this value actually needs to be set to 0.5.
And when all the parameters are set, we are
basically ready to go.
The software gets us to our results in a few
steps. You start by importing a recorded interferogram
and define the areas you wish to include or
exclude in the wavefront evaluation. If that
is done, the software performs a 2D Fourier
transform on the selected area and allows
us to do a bit of low-frequency spatial filtering.
This filtering can for example remove low
spatial frequencies that are result of the
global intensity variations due to uneven
illumination over the full surface. And after
setting the low-frequency spatial filter,
the image is resampled to a specific size
and from this, the software calculates the
wavefront data.
When the software calculates the wavefront,
it also fits the data to a specific set of
known aberrations. And this feature allows
for removing specific aberrations from your
analysis. For instance, tilt is generally
not an aberration of interest because it describes
the orientation between the reference and
the wavefront under test. And so it has nothing
to do with the shape of either surface. Now,
DFT-fringe allows you to either include or
exclude it from your analysis. You can customize
the presentation of the results and the scale.
For example you can convert wavefront errors
to surface shape errors and choose to present
them in nanometers instead of waves. All in
all, this is a very useful tool for interferometric
fringe analysis and on top of that it can
be downloaded for free.
In all upcoming experiments I will use this
F/0.75 transmission sphere as a reference.
And as I mentioned in the introduction, we
don’t know anything about its accuracy of
shape. So, before we can measure any meaningful
results with it, we need to measure the accuracy
of the reference sphere first. But how do
we do that? We could of course calibrate the
surface of the transmission sphere by comparing
its shape to a more precise reference surface.
But instead, I want to show you another method,
known as the “random ball” method.
The method requires the use of a small smooth
ball with a reflective surface. The surface
of the ball doesn't need to be perfectly spherical,
but I guess it helps if it is quite close-to-spherical.
Now the only thing we need to do for the experiment
is to measure the surface shape of the ball
at many random positions with the reference
sphere and then average these measurements.
The reason that this works is that, if you
collect a lot of samples from a ball surface
even if it’s far from perfect, all the errors
in individual parts of the surface will eventually
average out, and the average will iterate
to the surface equivalent of a perfect sphere.
And when you get to that point, the only error
that remains is the surface error in the reference
sphere because it is systematically present
in all the individual measurements.
You can buy these special high-accuracy SiC
balls for this purpose and these are pretty
expensive. However, there is a much cheaper
way: I just used a precision aluminum oxide
bearing ball that typically costs less than
25 euros online. The largest balls generally
have a diameter of around 10mm and have a
variation in the diameter of about 1 micron.
So they're not incredibly precise, but as
you will see, precise enough for this experiment.
To hold the ball, I made a stand from 3 quarter-inch
bearing balls, glued on top of an aluminum
rod using epoxy. And now we have a calibration
setup ready for less than 30 Euros.
The calibration procedure itself involves
placing this ball at the center of the radius
of curvature of the transmission sphere in
some random orientation. We record an interferogram,
then choose a different (random) area on the
ball, record another one and so on.
Here is what evaluating the results looks
like in practice: what you observe is that
in the individual measurements, the surface
error is generally larger than ¼ of a lambda
and is all over the place. And this is due
to the errors present in the shape of the
ball. But look what happens when we start
averaging these measurements: After 10 measurements,
the error has basically dropped down to 1/10th
of a lambda P-V. And by adding more and more
measurement to the average, we can gradually
bring this down even further. Until after
evaluating about 50 interferograms, we do
not see improvement any more in the result.
And at that point we know that the error that
remains is basically the error in the transmission
sphere reference.
If we look at the accuracy of shape in the
spherical reference, it is about 1/20 of a
wavelength peak to valley. And we will consider
this to be the wavefront accuracy over the
full area of the transmission sphere. Now
in all the upcoming tests, we will only use
a small fraction of this reference surface,
which will make the accuracy of the tests
quite a bit higher than the 1/20th of a lambda.
DFTfringe presents the value of the Strehl
ratio quite prominently. And I actually discussed
Strehl ratio in another video. Now I must
admit, Strehl ratio is not the most common
parameter used in the specification of the
optical quality of lenses. But for specifying
wavefront performance close to the diffraction
limit, I think it is a very useful parameter.
What it describes is basically just the ratio
between where wave energy actually ends up
in an image, compared to where it should have
ended up if the optic were perfect. So here
is a graph of an intensity profile of an imperfect
optic and of a perfect optic. To calculate
the Strehl we take the area that is under
both curves and name this B, and then divide
this by the area under the perfect curve,
so area A. This represents the fraction of
the light energy that goes to where it should
have gone in an image.
Since Strehl ratio is a fraction, its value
is between 0 and 1. And a value of 1 only
applies to an optic that performs at the theoretical
limit. Now, roughly speaking, an optic with
a Strehl ratio value above 0.83 is considered
to be “diffraction limited” What this
doesn’t mean is that the optic is performing
perfectly in this region. It just means that
the dominant factor for reduced sharpness
is because of diffraction, for example because
of a limited aperture. And to a lesser degree
it is due to the imperfections in things like
surface shape. So, in a sense the value of
0.83 is similar to stating that ¼ lambda
Peak to valley wavefront error is “diffraction
limited”. Because both these values are
kind of arbitrary definitions of what is meant
by “diffraction limited”.
So our reference surface turns out to be very
accurate, as we can conclude from both the
Strehl value as well as from the PV wavefront
error. But of course, that is kind of essential
if you want to use it to measure optical quality
of other objects in the high-end of the range.
The first thing we are going to measure is
the surface shape of this spherical Zerodur
mirror. It’s about 250mm in diameter and
has a radius of curvature of 350mm. I bought
the mirror about 10 years ago on eBay for
around 100 Euros. The reflective coating was
in pretty bad shape, so I removed it. But
the remaining surface reflectivity is 4%,
which is ideal in this test setup. The mirror
itself is from a 1970s Perkin-Elmer wafer
scanner system. This was the first commercial
photolithographic system that used non-contact
exposure of silicon wafers. So given its original
application, you’d expect this mirror to
be quite accurate.
The way we measure this mirror is with the
focus of the reference element in the center
of the radius of curvature of the mirror.
So, the tightly focused light beam from the
interferometer expands and reflects off the
mirror surface. It then returns along approximately
the same path and is recombined with the spherical
reference wavefront that reflects of the reference
element. And any deviations from spherical
in the mirror surface will cause phase shifts
between the light reflecting off the mirror
surface and the spherical reference. And this
can then be observed as interference.
Here are a few typical interferograms that
were measured with this mirror under a slight
tilt. Even though the mirror is strongly curved,
you can observe that in the measurements,
it only covers about half the diameter of
the total measurement area available. And
this makes our accuracy of measurement much
higher than 1/20th of a wavelength.
So from the interferograms just collected,
the wavefront differences between the mirror
surface and that of the reference element
is calculated in DFTfringe. you can see that
the peak to valley accuracy of this mirror
itself is around 1/10th of a wavelength. In
terms of surface shape accuracy, this means
that the mirror never deviates more than around
30nm of that of a perfect sphere. Anyway,
being able to measure with this level of precision
is actually pretty cool and it gave me confidence
that the instrument performs as expected.
By the way, if you have ever tried to make
a telescope mirror by hand yourself, you might
observe something familiar in the wavefron
plot: the mirror has a slightly turned down
edge, although very small, around 15nm or
so.
Next on the list of items to test is this
Canon FD 55mm F/1.2 lens. This is a rather
famous vintage lens in the sense that it was
actually the first consumer lens containing
an aspherical element. With its F/1.2 aperture,
it’s very light sensitive and therefore
well suited for indoor photography without
using a flash. The earliest versions of this
lens introduced in 1971, contained radioactive
Thorium Oxide, but this one, which was bought
by my father in march 1980, does not contain
Thorium. Therefore, it also does not display
the characteristic radiation browning observed
in radioactive lenses. On top of that it has
lived in a box most of its life so it’s
in nearly pristine condition.
For testing the wavefront deformation in this
lens, we utilize a configuration called autocollimation,
which is schematically depicted here. Because
the light passes through the lens twice in
this test, many aberrations are measured to
be twice as large as they would be with a
single pass. So when this configuration is
used, it requires us to interpret the fringe
spacing as equivalent with only 0.5 wavelength
instead of 1 wavelength.
Before I show you the result of the measurement,
I should mention that doing a wavefront measurement
on a lens is not in any way representative
for overall lens performance. Basically, we
are testing with only one particular wavelength
of light on the optical axis with the focus
setting to infinity. So, factors like chromatic
aberrations, off-axis performance in the image
field and the at proximity are not included
in this test. I've actually made a video on
how to quantitatively measure all these aspects
using another method and obtain a more holistic
performance. But even with all the limitations,
I think it is worthwhile to take a look at
the wavefront error that this lens introduces.
So here is the wavefront error of the lens
at its full aperture and as you can see, it’s
is actually pretty large. The total P-V wavefront
error is more than 3 lambda and the most apparent
errors are spherical aberration and some astigmatisms.
The Strehl ratio is quite disappointing as
well. As a consequence, this lens can never
provide high sharpness images at the maximum
aperture. Now, it’s interesting to see what
happens if we limit the aperture of this lens
to let’s say to F/4.0. By doing that, we
will lose a lot of light, about 90%. But this
also limits the wavefront error to the one
present in this central part here. So, if
we do the same wavefront analysis at F/4,
suddenly the lens performs diffraction limited.
Because reducing aperture to F/4 eliminates
almost all of the spherical error and the
astigmatism which is present in the wavefront
at full aperture.
Here is a comparison of the text on a permanent
marker shot with F/1.2 and F/4 on an aps-c
sensor. It’s clear that the 3-lambda wavefront
error is influencing the sharpness and contrast
pretty badly. So, I guess the only way to
use this lens effectively is to always set
it to a smaller aperture whenever there is
sufficient light available, otherwise you’ll
end up with very soft images.
The Canon EF 24 to 105mm full frame zoom lens
is next on our list. I just want to take a
very brief look at it, mainly because I sometimes
use it for my YouTube videos. With its maximum
aperture of F/4 over the whole zoom range
it is not particularly photon hungry. But
it always produces excellent image sharpness,
which made me curious about how small the
wavefront errors in a high-quality lens are.
It was measured in the same way as the F/1.2
lens, so in autocollimation. And here are
the wavefront errors at focal length settings
of 24mm, 50mm and 105mm. The largest wavefront
errors are found at 105mm focal distance,
where the Strehl ratio has dropped to 0.6.
Which by the way is still a very decent value.
In the center of the range, its performance
is basically diffraction limited. So concluding:
this lens performs well in the full zoom range.
That is of course, within all the limitations
of the current testing method.
If you made it this far into the video you
are probably more than averagely interested
in optics. So, for this last part I thought
I’d present measurements that I did on microscope
objectives. All objectives presented here
are all so called “infinity corrected”
objectives. This means that they are designed
to work in combination with a so-called tube
lens rather than create an image directly
like is the case with a proximity-corrected
objectives. Since infinity corrected objectives
basically project their image at infinity,
this allows us to correctly use the autocollimation
configuration for testing.
Unlike camera lenses, microscope objectives
aren't specified by focal length and maximum
focal distance to aperture ratio. Instead,
they are characterized by magnification and
numerical aperture. I’ll very briefly discuss
these two aspects first.
Magnification describes the ratio between
the object size and image size that a particular
microscope objective is designed for. You
can of course try to use it at a different
magnification by changing both the lens-object
distance and the lens-image distance. But
if you do that, it will not perform optimally.
And this is important because microscope optics
is required to work close to the theoretical
best performance. So in this sense, a microscope
objective is a bit different from a camera
lens, which is basically designed to give
you acceptable image quality over a wide range
of object to lens distances.
Now, specifying a high magnification is only
useful if the sharpness in the image keeps
up with the magnification that is specified.
And that is why the Magnification and Numerical
Aperture of objectives are related, because
Numerical Aperture is a key parameter for
resolving small features.
By definition, the NA is equal to the refractive
index of the medium that contains the object,
times the SIN() of the maximum angle theta
at which light originating from the object
can be captured. This means that NA increases
with the refractive index of the medium and
with the value of theta. Now, since all the
objectives I will discuss today are intended
for use in air and not in water- or oil, we
can simplify things because the refractive
index of air is 1. So for now we can just
ignore the refractive index which means that
NA in all cases discussed here is just equal
to the sin() of theta.
The exact reason why NA is the key parameter
for achieving a high sharpness is quite fascinating.
But it is kind of a rabbit hole, which I don’t
want to dive into now. Today I will just show
you the formula. So, the size of the smallest
features that can theoretically be resolved
by a microscope objective are proportional
to a constant, times the wavelength of light,
divided by the numerical aperture. This means
that it is possible to resolve smaller features
by either using a shorter wavelength of light,
or use a higher NA.
This relationship explains why magnification
and numerical aperture are so closely related
in the specification of microscope objectives.
Because attempting to pair a high magnification
with a low numerical aperture is pretty useless:
it will just result in a magnified image of
poor sharpness.
Let’s have a look at the measurements on
this Nikon 10x objective with a N.A. of 0.3.
Here is an image of the wavefront error of
this objective and it shows us that the errors
are in fact very small. The wavefront is accurate
within seven hundredths of a wavelength for
the entire aperture, the Strehl is 0.99, so
this is looking great. The major contribution
in the surface error is actually a very slight
spherical aberration, but all in all, this
is really a top-quality piece.
Now, let's examine a different objective,
like this 20x Leica Fluotar with a NA of 0.5,
and do the same wavefront measurement. Interestingly,
the spherical aberration in this objective
is noticably more pronounced. Both the total
peak-valley error as well as the Strehl ratio
is only just on the good side of the diffraction
limit. Now, it might be tempting to conclude
that this objective is not as good as the
previous one, but that's not the case. The
reason behind the spherical aberration is
in this particular number that can be found
on the objective. The number represents the
optimum cover slip thickness in millimeters
for this objective.
So, what the manufacturer assumes is that
you are going to use a glass cover slip when
you use your microscope and it therefore it
has already compensated the optical properties
for a specific glass thickness. Now, you might:
think huh 0.17mm of glass thickness, how is
that ever going to influence the focus? And
indeed, with low numerical aperture optics
there will generally not be a problem. However,
with increasing NA, even a glass plate this
thin can introduce a significant spherical
aberration. This is illustrated in this ray
tracing figure for a 0.7 NA. In a perfect
optic, all rays will end in a single point.
But add a cover glass and suddenly the area
where the rays end up has significant size.
Now of course the previous wavefront measurement
was done without a cover slip. So, the question
is what happens if we add a cover slip in
the light path? I quickly tried this with
a glass thickness of 0.16mm, so close to the
optimum value and it resulted in this measurement:
it reduced the spherical aberration quite
a bit. And so, this is something to realize
when you use a high-NA objectives: that it
can only perform at its peak performance when
used in combination with the cover slip thickness
specified.
So a few years ago, I bought this unmarked
NIKON 20x Plan APO OEM objective for use in
my maskless wafer stepper. These Nikon objectives
can be purchased on eBay for around 100 dollars
apiece and are widely available. It was in
perfect shape when it got here but when I
started using it, something was a bit off,
dependent on how I used it exactly. Now, when
I published the video on the maskless wafer
stepper, people at a forum called photomicrography.net
made me aware of the fact that these particular
types of objectives aren't optically the same
as the corresponding standard Nikon microscope
objectives; they are actually modified versions
that are designed for a different cover slip
thickness. The forum thread on this subject
mentioned that these perform better when used
in combination with 2 or 3 cover slips. And
since I now have an interferometer available
let’s see if we can narrow this value down
a bit further.
Here is the spherical aberration of the objective
without a cover slip. The wavefront error
is 1 lambda, so without a correction, it will
certainly perform very poorly. Here I summarized
the individual wavefront measurements for
0, 1, 2, 3 and 4 cover slips. I think the
effect of adding more glass is pretty clear.
You can see that the wavefront error sort
of flips over between 2 and 3 cover slips
of glass thickness.
What we can do now is take for example the
peak to valley spherical aberration from these
measurements and plot the values as a function
of the total glass thickness in a graph. And
by fitting a line through these data, we find
that a minimum aberration is at around 0.42-0.43mm.
And this thickness is right between 2 and
3 cover slips, like it was stated on the forum.
Here is a similar graph that I made for the
maximum Strehl ratio, which yields exactly
the same outcome. So, if we were to add a
0.42 mm glass sheet when using it, we can
effectively get rid of the huge spherical
aberration completely and use this objective
at its maximum performance level again.
Okay, we’ve finally come to the end of the
video. I hope I gave you some ideas of how
interferometry can be used for optical testing.
Thanks for watching.