Hi everyone,
Today I want to talk about optical interferometry,
a method that is frequently used to measure the
properties of optical components and systems.
What initially made me want to do a video about
this subject is this ZYGO interferometer, that I
bought a while ago second hand. A new instrument
of this type is financially far out of my reach,
and I must admit, this one wasn’t a bargain
either. But the thing is, I’ve wanted to own
a high-quality interferometer for a long time,
if only to get away from the DIY-setups I’ve
used so far. And since these instruments are
not abundantly available second hand, I just
had to take this rare opportunity to buy one.
In case you have no idea what this instrument is:
with it you can very accurately measure the
shape of flat and spherical optical interfaces,
like the ones you find on lenses and mirrors. And
with accurately I mean: in the nanometer range.
But not only that, you can also measure the
performance of complete optical systems. So,
a good interferometer is an indispensable tool for
anyone involved in optical fabrication. Because
in the end, the quality of your optics is mainly
limited by the quality of your testing methods.
This particular instrument was produced
by ZYGO in August of 1996. It was sold
to Philips Electronics in Eindhoven,
where it was used to check the surface
shape of lenses for special optical
disk drives. From what I understood,
some of these lenses were produced from small
polished glass balls. These were cut in pieces,
and then transformed into very short
focal distance lenses. Now, at some point,
the activity was transferred to a Philips spin-off
called Anteryon and the interferometer was sold to
an employee, who basically stored it for a couple
of years. He then sold it to me, together with a
black and white monitor and the transmission
sphere that was used to test the lenses.
In this video, I’ll first discuss
the principle behind interferometry,
and then we will look at the layout of the
instrument and how it works exactly. And in
an upcoming video I will show how I pimped the
instrument a bit with a modern ccd camera.
As I said earlier, in optics manufacture,
interferometry is a frequently used method
to characterize both optical surfaces as well
as complete systems. The method is based on
analyzing interference patterns and extract so
called “wavefront” information from them and I
will discuss the meaning of the word wavefront in
a second. Interferometry is an extremely sensitive
and accurate method that can be used to establish
the general shape of an interface, but also things
like waviness or even surface roughness. It
does also have some limitations: The measurement
range is generally fairly limited to several
microns. Also, it’s unsuitable for interfaces that
contain sharp step-like height features, because
these cannot be unambiguously identified. So,
in general, interferometry is most accurate when
the surfaces we want to test are fairly smooth.
Now, I just mentioned the word “wavefront”,
which I think is not a trivial concept.
I guess we have all experienced wavefronts at some
point in our lives but I’m not referring to those.
In optics a wavefront is actually a continuous set
of points that have identical phase. So, what does
that mean? Well, from a classical viewpoint, light
is an electromagnetic field that harmonically
oscillates and propagates in space. And at any
given point in this process, the electric and
magnetic field components can be described by
the Maxwell equations. So here I’ve tried to
schematically draw the electromagnetic field in
a somewhat larger volume and if you examine the
phase of these waves, you can identify planes
where the phase of the electromagnetic field
is identical. And a continuous set of points that
have the same phase value is called a wavefront.
One property of a wavefront is that its shape
is always transverse or perpendicular to the
local direction of wave propagation. Here
this is illustrated for a few differently
shaped wavefronts where the arrows indicate the
direction of wave propagation. Now in general,
phase relationships for different points in
space are only well-defined when the waves
have one specific wavelength. And if we want to
do interferometry, it is vital that the light we
use is of one particular wavelength, which
is also called monochromatic light. And in
the rest of the video, I’ll assume that the
light used is more or less monochromatic.
A frequently used way to generate monochromatic
radiation is by means of a laser. This is because,
the process of stimulated emission which takes
place in the laser cavity, favors the generation
of light in a very narrow wavelength range.
Also, the wavefront exiting the laser cavity is
virtually flat over the aperture. And because the
light has an extremely well-defined wavelength,
in other words it has a very narrow spectral
bandwidth, phase relationships in the field
exiting the laser can be preserved over long
distances. Another way to say this is that lasers
have a large coherence length, which is generally
between half a meter up to several kilometers for
certain special types of lasers. In practice
this means that, if we take 2 points A and B in
the light path and we look at the variations in
the phase difference between these 2 points, we
will find that these will be relatively small. And
the distance over which variations in phase remain
acceptable is called the coherence length. As you
can see from this equation, the coherence length
(Lc) is inversely proportional to the spectral
band width (delta nu) of the light source. And
so light sources with a very narrow emission line
will generally have a long coherence length.
Another source of monochromatic light frequently
used in interferometry is the low-pressure sodium
lamp, which mainly generates light in a
narrow emission band at 589nm. However,
the spectral bandwidth of the Sodium emission
line is much broader than that of lasers and
the phase relationships generally only
hold over distances smaller than a mm.
Now, measuring the shape of a wavefront
directly in the visible part of the
electromagnetic spectrum is not easy and that is
because of the very high frequencies involved.
For electromagnetic radiation of longer
wavelengths, like for example radio waves,
we can measure the phase of the alternating fields
directly. And that is because the oscillations
have a relatively low frequency, say generally
somewhere in the mega- or giga- Hertz range.
And so, we can point a bunch of antennas to the
sky, measure the Electromagnetic signals that
are received in each of them and establish the
shape of the wavefront for a particular frequency
by looking for phase correlations. And based on
this information we can then identify the exact
direction from which the radiation is emitted. But
visible light has a frequency more than a thousand
times higher than even the highest frequency
radio waves. And for frequencies this high, it is
technically infeasible to measure phase directly
for an oscillating electromagnetic field.
However, what we can easily measure with
optical detectors, like CCD- or CMOS-sensors,
is spatial intensity variations. And
that is where interferometry comes in:
instead of trying to measure the phase in light
directly, this method works by studying the
interference patterns resulting from the addition
of a second wavefront that has a known shape.
Let me start by showing you a very simple
example of how this works in light.
For this experiment we need a monochromatic
light source and a flat surface. As a light
source we’ll use a sodium lamp and for the
surface we will use a flat optical test glass.
Now, a typical air-glass interface
reflects about 4% of the incident light
and with a uniform light source,
we observe a uniform reflection.
Let’s now place 2 differently shaped surfaces on
top of this reference surface for evaluation. What
we observe is that these objects show 2 different
interference patterns. The part to the left,
shows straight lines with equal spacing. And the
one to the right, displays these curved lines or
circular fringes, depending on the exact surface
orientation. Now, it’s these intensity variations
that actually contain detailed information about
the difference in shape between reference surface
and the two surfaces under test. We just need
to know how to interpret what we see exactly.
So, what do we see? Well let me explain with
an animation. I admit, the following is a
simplification and it’s not correctly visualizing
the physics, but it’s actually quite illustrative.
Here is a wavefront that has just reflected off
a flat reference surface, so this wavefront is
basically also flat. And so the image shows a
2D cross section of the flat optical wavefronts.
If we place a sensor in the path of the
light, we can measure the intensity,
and what we observe is that it is basically the
same everywhere and this tells us exactly nothing
about the shape of the wavefront. Now, let’s add
a second wavefront that has reflected of a second
surface that is slightly tilted. In this example
the wavefront is also flat and what we observe
is that the intensity now becomes non-uniformly.
And this is caused by constructive and destructive
interference between the 2 reflected wavefronts
at the second interface. Here, the electromagnetic
field is the linear sum of the contributions
of the fields of the 2 wavefronts. And so,
in some points where these contributions are
always in phase, they add up. On the other hand,
in places where the two are exactly in out
of phase, the field contributions cancel each
other out and if they are of equal amplitude,
effectively the resulting field becomes zero.
In the case of 2 flat wavefronts, we will observe
linear and equally spaced fringes. The density of
the interference pattern itself is dependent
on the wedge or angle between the surfaces.
And the position of the fringes is dependent
on the distance between the two surfaces. Now,
you might think that linear and equally spaced
fringes are indicative for the presence of 2 flat
surfaces. And that is partly correct, but 2 curved
wavefronts with the same radius of curvature will
actually also display linear and equally spaced
fringes, when displaced or tilted. However,
when two wavefronts have different radii, this
results in curved fringes. This is for example
the case when we have a flat- and a spherical
wavefront interfering. Or when we have 2 spherical
wavefronts that have a different radius curvature.
So, I guess it is important to realize that
the observed interference pattern only gives us
information about differences in wavefront shape.
In the example just shown with the sodium lamp
light, we only observe interference between
interfaces when they are placed very close
together. And that is because of the limited
coherence length of the light. So whether we see a
clear interference pattern is dependent on whether
stable phase relationships exist between the
reflections coming off the two surfaces at the
point where they start interfering. This means
that with a coherence length smaller than a mm,
the surfaces need to be quite close to each
other in order to observe interference fringes.
Now I just stated that in constructive
interference, the electromagnetic fields
add up and in destructive interference, the
2 contributions cancel each other out. So,
what does this mean for intensity? Well,
light intensity is equivalent to the power
per unit of surface and so it is actually
not the same thing as the magnitude of
the electromagnetic field. In fact, intensity
scales with the square of this field. And so,
if we have 2 reflections of equal magnitude, say
both are 4%, this means that for the location of
constructive interference, intensity could be
4 times as high. And that is actually what is
generally observed in interference patterns:
that the intensity in the bright areas is
much brighter than the sum of the 2 individual
intensities. But of course, if we look on average,
the intensity over the whole area will still
equal to the sum of the 2 individual intensities.
Anyway, enough background. Let’s return to the
ZYGO interferometer itself and take a peek under
the hood to see what’s going on inside. In order
to do that we need to remove 2 different lids:
the outer one is made of plastic and is
basically just cosmetic. The second one is
made out of aluminum sheet metal and is intended
as RF-shielding for the electronics inside.
First thing you notice is, that it isn’t awfully
full inside. There is a helium Neon laser with
its high-voltage power supply. Then there are a
few optical components like a steering mirror for
the laser beam, a variable filter that can be
moved mechanically using a long rod. This rod
also operates a switch, that activates either of
2 pcb-cameras that are also found in the top part
of the interferometer. The cameras by the way
have CCD-chips of about 6x4mm in size and are
fairly low resolution. Both cameras have lenses
mounted in front of them. One of the camera is
above a tiny beam splitter, and the other one is
above a diffusor with a crosshair printed on it.
In the bottom compartment, behind the lid
here, we find a mains 12V DC power supply,
a large beam splitter, a mirror under 45
degrees and 4-inch collimation lens. And
apart from a few brackets and mounts that hold
the optics together, that is basically it.
So you might wonder: why was this thing the
price of a luxury car back in 1996? Well,
apart from I suspect a healthy profit margin,
there are several reasons: of course, it’s not
really a mass manufactured item. But another
reason is that every component inside appears
to be of very high quality. Take for example
the Helium Neon laser: according to the label,
the tube has been specifically selected for this
type of instrument. Why? Well, if we look at the
specification of the coherence length of the
interferometer, we see that it is larger than
100m. This means that the wavelength variations
in the laser light need to be extremely low,
so that phase relationships hold over distances of
more than 100m. Now, I calculated what this means
in terms of frequency stability and found that
variations in the frequency of the 632nm light
cannot be more than 2. 10-7 percent. And so, this
means that not just any random laser will do.
So let me take you through the functionality of
all the components step by step using schematics.
Here is the Helium-Neon laser, which
outputs a highly coherent beam of
light. The direction of the beam can be
optimized with a small steering mirror,
after which the beam goes through the variable
attenuation filter. This filter allows adjustment
of the general brightness of the laser beam.
After having passed the attenuation filter, the
beam is going into a gradient index lens, which
is connected to a very small beam splitter.
Now, a gradient index lens is a small glass rod
that contains a gradient in refractive index,
that runs from the center to edge of the rod.
Since the refractive index has the highest value
in the center, the optical wave front in the
laser beam is gradually delayed more towards
the center of the rod. The wavefront therefore
becomes curved, which effectively results in
focusing of the light into a tight focal point.
And after passing this focal point, the beam
expands again into a nicely spherical wavefront. A
small beam splitter sends the spherical wavefront
to the partially reflective surface of a
second, much larger beam splitter. This
surface reflects the light towards a collimation
lens, where the light exits the instrument.
The function of the collimation lens is to
convert the spherical wavefront into a flat
wavefront of 4 inches in diameter. And this
flat wavefront can serve as the basis for all
kinds of interferometric tests. For example, we
can place 2 partially reflective flat interfaces
into this output beam, one being a reference
interface and one being the interface that
we like to test for flatness. And due to
the large coherence length of the light,
more than 100m, these interfaces don’t have
the be necessarily very close together.
The light reflecting off these surfaces
is directed back into the interferometer
approximately along the same path as it came
from, goes through the small beam splitter
again and is then collimated and projected on
a CCD chip. And this allows us to observe the
interference pattern between the 2 reflections
and evaluate this visually on the monitor.
Now, to steer the light of both the reference
and test surface exactly back through the tiny
beam splitter here, is pretty hard. And
you don’t see anything with camera 1,
until things are almost perfectly aligned. So, to
make life a lot easier, the people at ZYGO added
this alignment functionality to the system. Part
of the light from the reflections can pass this
larger beam splitter. This part continues straight
on, is reflected at a 90 degrees angle and then
reaches a glass diffuser plate that contains a
cross-hair pattern. Because this diffusor plate is
exactly at the focal distance of the collimation
lens, the reflections create tiny spots here. And
their positions can be observed by camera 2 that
is only intended for alignment purposes. Now,
this alignment unit has a much larger field of
view and what we can do now is simply align the
position of surface reflections such that they
are at the center of the cross-hair. And when
that is the case, the system is automatically also
aligned on camera 1 and we can immediately observe
an interferogram. Now, the interferometers
that I made myself did not have this kind of
feature and it must admit that this makes
aligning optics really a piece of cake.
Here you see the location of the collimation
lens, viewed from the outside of the instrument.
In front of it is an adjustment mechanism
that is intended for mounting various
reference surfaces to the interferometer
directly, like the F/0.75 transmission
sphere that came with the interferometer. The
adjustment mechanism has 2 degrees of freedom,
which are tip and tilt. This allows the angle of
the transmission reference to be oriented with
respect to the surface under test.
When testing optical components,
you generally test the surface shape before
the interfaces get coated. And so in the case
of glass this means that they reflect around 4% of
the incident light. So, the transmission reference
also needs to reflect around 4% back into the
interferometer to get high-contrast fringes.
To test spherical surfaces, you need a spherical
reference surface that somehow reflects 4% of the
light exiting the interferometer right back into
the instrument. Now the way this is achieved is as
follows: here I’ve drawn a schematic of the inside
of a transmission sphere assembly to show you how
that is achieved. The reference surface is the
last interface of the assembly, here indicated in
yellow. All the other surfaces are anti-reflection
coated for the laser wavelength, but even more
importantly, they are also designed in such a way,
that the light reaches the reference interface
exactly perpendicular. And this means that it is
the only interface in the transmission sphere that
sends a reflection back where it came from and
then enters the interferometer as a collimated
beam. Of course, 96% of the light continues on
to the surface under test, which also reflects
around 4%. And so we observe the interference
occurring between these 2 interfaces.
With a spherical transmission reference, we
can test convex- as well as concave optics.
For convex optics, only radii smaller than the
radius of the transmission sphere itself can be
tested. For concave optics, the only limitation
for the radius to be tested is that it should be
less than half of the maximum coherence length
of the light source which is in this case 50m.
Now I want to save most of the experiments
that I had in mind for another video,
but let’s just do one simple experiment. For
this test, we’ll just use the flat wavefront
exiting the instrument. And what we will try to
measure is the difference in shape between the
2 surfaces of a Zerodur test glass. This test
glass has one side which I know is very flat,
around 1/20th of a wavelength. And this is
going to be our reference interface. But the
other side is somewhat less flat. And what
we’ll try to find out is how much that is.
The two interfaces are spaced 20 mm apart and
both reflect about 4% of the incident light. So
we can just place the disk in the beam exiting
the interferometer, align the position of the
2 reflections simultaneously and then look at
the interference pattern. And this is what it
looks like. As you can see, we get a nice and
clear interference pattern, which by the way is
extremely stable with no effects of vibrations
from the environment. That is because the two
surfaces are basically mechanically connected
to each other by a solid piece of Zerodur.
Now, the small circular spots are just dust
particles in the optical path and these are
not important for our evaluation. All the
information about the difference in shape
and orientation between the 2 surfaces is
contained in the 4 more or less vertical
fringes. And because we know that
one side is almost perfectly flat,
any curvature in the fringe pattern is the
result of non-flatness of the second surface.
So, let’s try to evaluate this pattern visually.
The most obvious feature is of course the presence
of the 4 vertical fringes, that indicate that
there is a wedge between the 2 interfaces in
horizontal direction. And we can calculate how
large this wedge is, based on the number of
fringes. It is a little over 4 Lambda wavefront,
meaning that there is a wedge half of that between
the 2 surfaces, so just 2 wavelengths. Why
half? Well, that is because in reflection,
any deviations in surface shape, lead to twice
the deviation in the wavefront shape. And so,
deviations in surface shape are only
half of that observed in the wavefront.
Now, since the wavelength of the laser is 632.8nm
and the wedge is 2 lambda between the 2 surface
this, would mean a gradient in distance of
approx. 1.3 microns. But there is a little
catch in this case. Because we are comparing 2
surfaces with Zerodur between them, we should
actually use the wavelength in this material.
Which means that we should divide the wavelength
in air or vacuum by the refractive index of
Zerodur, which is 1.54. So this means that the
wedge is actually only 840nm. But which side is
thicker? It’s hard to tell because as for wedge,
we would see the same type of interference pattern
in either case. So at this point, we don’t know.
Okay, let’s for a moment focus on the curvature
of the fringes now, which indicates a difference
in the radius between the 2 surfaces. If
we look at how much the curvature in the
fringes deviates from a straight line, we see
that it is largest here in the center, and it
is about 0.4 times the fringe spacing, which
translates to 0.4 wavelength of height difference
between edge and center of the disk. For the
surface error, which again is half of that,
we find 0.2 wavelengths, Now, since we also
need to use the wavelength inside Zerodur here,
this means that the surface curvature is 0.2*times
the wavelength divided by the refractive index,
which results in a value of 82nm. But
in which direction is the curve? Is the
surface under test 82nm concave or convex? As
with the direction of the wedge, there is no
easy way to tell. So now we end up with these 4
configurations of which only one can be correct.
With a little logic though, you could at this
point already discard 2 of these as infeasible.
But of course, you want to know exactly which
configuration of the 4 is correct, right?
So, if that is indeed the case, figure it out
yourself. You just need a 2 more pieces of
information. Here is the first hint: if I press
my finger against the backside of the disk,
so on the surface under test, we can observe
that the interferogram changes due to temperature
increase of the material by the heat of my finger.
Locally, it is only a few degrees Celsius higher,
but the effect is very noticeable because
we are measuring in the nanometer range.
Now, the second piece of information you need
is about the expansion coefficient of the
material. As you can see from the specifications
of Zerodur, it can be either positive or negative.
But this piece of Zerodur has a positive
coefficient of thermal expansion, which
means it expands with temperature increase. And
with these 2 additional pieces of information,
it is possible tell which of these 4 options
is correct. Now, the first person to make
a comment with the correct answer and
course why, owns the pinned comment.
Okay, so the latter was a very brief explanation
of how you can evaluate interferograms visually.
And, the above example was actually relatively
easy. Imagine your interferogram looks something
like this. Or this. In these cases, it would be
quite a bit more challenging to make accurate
statements about the exact surface shape. This
is why in the next video about this subject,
I have replaced the current analog camera with a
high-resolution IP-camera. This allows for very
detailed evaluation of interferograms using
software. And with the help of this software,
we can measure wedges, angles, surface
curvature, and even the effects of warm
fingers very accurately. Also, we will take a look
at how to measure the shape of various optical
surfaces, and the quality of lens assemblies. So,
hopefully I’ll see you in the next video again.